Guide to the Rioghan Kirchner Civil Rights in Brooklyn Collection BCMS.0011
Brooklyn Collection
Rioghan Kirchner Civil Rights in Brooklyn Collection
1960-2005
1960-1969
Brooklyn Collection
Kirchner, Rioghan, -2013.
BCMS.0011
5.2 Linear Feet in 10 boxes
A collection of material related to the 1960s civil rights movement in the United States, particularly the Brooklyn chapter of CORE (Congress of Racial Equality) and the Brooklyn group FOCUS (Freedom Organizations Coordinated for Unity in Shorefront), compiled by Rioghan Kirchner, a member of Brooklyn CORE and cofounder of FOCUS.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains both primary source materials documenting the work of CORE, FOCUS and other Brooklyn groups during the 1960s as well as secondary source materials such as newspaper and magazine articles that refer to ongoing civil rights struggles on the national stage.
Series I covers Brooklyn CORE actions against employment discrimination, housing and school discrimination, as well as the organization's participation in the March on Washington in 1963. It also includes documents relating to legal cases and photographs of actions and individual activists.
Series II contains FOCUS newsletters and other materials relating to FOCUS and their work on housing discrimination.
Series III is a compilation of books, articles, typescripts and ephemera on various aspects of the civil rights movement.
Series IV consists of a run of facsimile copies of the newsletter Black News (124 issues from October 1969 to March 1984).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series by subject. The individual series arrangement is as follows: Series I is arranged by subject. Series II is also arranged by subject except for the newsletters, which are arranged chronologically. Series III is arranged by type of media and the subseries are arranged chronologically. Series IV is arranged chronologically.
Historical Note
CORE (Congress of Racial Equality) was a national civil rights organization founded in Chicago in 1942. The Brooklyn chapter was founded in 1960 by Dr. Robert Palmer, Marjorie Leeds, and a group of other local community activists specifically to address living conditions in the predominantly Black neighborhood of Bedford-Stuyvesant: poor quality housing, inadequate garbage collection, inferior schools, and high unemployment. From 1960-1964, members of Brooklyn CORE led local demonstrations to desegregate housing, integrate public schools, create jobs, and improve sanitation services in Bedford-Stuyvesant. The organization was one of the most dynamic civil rights groups in New York City at the time.
FOCUS (Freedom Organizations Coordinated for Unity in Shorefront) was another Brooklyn group that made significant contributions to the civil rights movement. Working out of the Sheepshead Bay-Shorefront area, the group was instrumental in suspending the licenses of several real estate brokers who discriminated in selling and renting houses and apartments. They also took direct action against violators of public accommodations such as the American Legion and Cabana Clubs. Their Operation Open City was active in obtaining housing for minority families who had been discriminated against.
Black News was a semi-monthly newsletter produced in Bedford-Stuyvesant from 1969 to 1984. The photocopied publication was created and distributed entirely by volunteers. According to its first issue, it was "a community publication" and "it was formed in order to encourage a new awareness and involvement among our people." With articles on police brutality, racist government policies, corrupt politicians, health and medicine, and the "P.O.W. Forum"—a series on Black people in prisons—as well as poetry and artwork, Black News worked to fulfill its mission to "agitate, educate, [and] organize."
Biographical Note
Rioghan Kirchner was born in Liverpool, England. After immigrating to Canada, she met and married an American man, Paul Kirchner, and the two of them moved to Brooklyn, New York in 1955. Her first job in the United States was as a clerk at the Kings Bay branch of Brooklyn Public Library. Soon after earning a degree from Brooklyn College, she started working in the Domestic Violence Unit of South Brooklyn Legal Services, where she worked for many years. When she retired in 1987, she was working as a legislative assistant to the City Council.
Inspired by the Southern Freedom Riders, she joined the Brooklyn chapter of CORE (Congress of Racial Equality) in 1961, and soon took on an active role in the organization. Kirchner worked as a "tester," masquerading as a potential renter to landlords suspected of housing discrimination in order to identify those who denied rental opportunities based on race. She went on to become Housing Chairman and then Vice-Chairman of Brooklyn CORE. Later, she helped start FOCUS (Freedom Organization Coordinated Unity in Shorefront) and organized their campaign against real estate brokers engaged in discriminatory housing practices.
Kirchner passed away in 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Rioghan Kirchner, 2003-2005.
Related Materials
Center for Brooklyn History Civil Rights Research Guide
Arnie Goldwag Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) collection (ARC 002)
Bob Adelman photographs of Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) demonstrations (V1989.022)
Brian Purnell Civil Rights in Brooklyn Oral History Collection (BCMS.0012)
Brian Purnell research papers (2015.034)
Richetta Randolph Wallace papers, 1906-1971 (1978.137)
August Meier and Elliott Rudwick. CORE: a study in the civil rights movement, 1942-1968. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1975.
Brian Purnell. A movement grows in Brooklyn: the Brooklyn chapter of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) and the northern civil rights movement during the early 1960's. Ann Arbor, MI: UMI 2006.
Brian Purnell. Fighting Jim Crow in the County of Kings: the Congress of Racial Equality in Brooklyn. Lexington, KY: University Press of Kentucky, 2013.
Clarence Taylor. The Black churches of Brooklyn. New York, NY: Columbia University Press, 1994.
Craig Steven Wilder. A covenant with color: race and social power in Brooklyn. New York, NY: Columbia University Press, 2000.
Jeanne Theoharis and Komozi Woodard, eds. Groundwork: local black freedom movements in America. New York, NY: New York University, 2005.
Civil rights movements -- United States -- 20th century; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Race relations -- United States; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Series I: Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) - Brooklyn chapter
  - Fast for Freedom, 1961 August (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Route 40 Restaurant Discrimination, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Operation Clean Sweep documents and clippings, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Operation Clean Sweep photographs, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Operation Federal Intervention Georgia - picket of White House, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - St. John's Hospital segregation clippings, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - North Star CORE Newsletter, 1962 December (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - General CORE documents, 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Brooklyn Ministers' Coalition, 1962-2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CORE clippings and information, circa 1963-2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rent Strikes, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - World's Fair stall-in clippings, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - World's Fair stall-in - Brian Purnell essay, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - People of CORE
    Scope and Contents
    The materials in these folders include clippings, documents, ephemera and photographs.
    - Bibuld, Elaine, 1964, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bibuld family photographs, 1992-2004 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Dickerson, Eddie, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Farmer, James, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Goldwag, Arnold, 1963-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Kirchner, Rioghan, 1962-2014 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Leeds, Oliver, circa 1960s-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lewinson, Prof. Edward, 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Owens, Major, 1964-2005 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - School Discrimination
    - School Discrimination and Bibuld Case clippings, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - School Discrimination and Bibuld Case documents, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Board of Education sit-in photographs, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - School integration clippings, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Housing Discrimination
    - Cases: documents, clippings, and photos, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
      These folders include documentation of the following cases: Beverly family, Whiting family versus Molo Construction, Ruth Diamond/Majestic Realty versus Greaves, Lefrak Organization, Ira Management versus Margaret Chapman, Lawson versus Nieman, Ginsberg versus Ryan, Safrin and Safrin, Christie-Jacobovitz, Cole versus Vandeveer Estate, White Bros. versus Cohn and Kahn, and Weiner-McGuire.
    - Commission on Human Rights poster regarding housing complaints (oversize), circa 1960-1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Clippings, 1963-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Braithwaite case, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Henderson vs. Wurman, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - "Why Not Next Door?" by Rioghan Kirchner, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Employment Discrimination
    - Ebinger's Bakery documents and clippings, 1954-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Ebinger's Bakery photographs, circa 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Downstate Medical Center documents and clippings, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Sealtest, White Castle, Wolfie's documents and clippings, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Freedom Organizations Coordinated for Unity in Shorefront (FOCUS)
  - FOCUS and related neighborhood news and history clippings, 1959-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Public Accommodations in Manhattan Beach and Sheepshead Bay, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Committee on Preservation of a Self-Integrated Community (Copsic), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letter from Ira Gruber, 1965 December 22 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Low-income housing on Emmons Avenue clippings, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Operation Open City, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Real estate brokers, clippings, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Real estate brokers, documents, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Housing Committee tester's handbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Sheepshead Bay: A Pictorial Tour" by Rioghan Kirchner, circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - FOCUS Newsletter
    - Volume 1, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Volume 2, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
    - Volume 3, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - In Memoriam Dorothy Fulmer, 1967 February (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Also includes clippings about Fulmer's death.
    - Original cartoons, circa 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series III: Civil Rights publications, clippings, and ephemera
  - National CORE publications, circa 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Civil Rights clippings, 1961-2005, bulk 1963-1965; 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Civil Rights pins, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - March on Washington documents, clippings, and ephemera, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "General Instructions for Coach Operators" document for March on Washington (oversize), 1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Facsimile copy of August 29, 1963 issue of the New York Times with coverage of the March on Washington, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - CORE hats, circa 1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Historical Note
    Worn at the March on Washington.
  - Louis Lo Monaco March on Washington poster (2 copies), 1963 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Louis Lo Monaco artwork, circa 1963 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Civil Rights documents and ephemera, circa 1964-1968, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Police brutality clippings, documents and photographs, 1964-1999 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Howard Beach hate crime clippings, 1986-1987, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Civil Rights publications
    - Freedomways, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - We Shall Overcome!, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Civil Rights and Civil Wrongs, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - The Movement, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Malcom X Speaks, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Troubled Summer, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Rights and Reviews, 1966-1967 Winter (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Concerning Dissent, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - A Political Biography of Angela Davis, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Free At Last magazine, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Poems of Protest [Part 1] (Box 4)
      A compilation of photocopied protest poems and images apparently compiled by Rioghan Kirchner.
    - Poems of Protest [Part 2] (Box 5)
- Series IV: Black News
  Black News was a semi-monthly newsletter produced in Bedford-Stuyvesant from 1969 to 1984. The photocopied publication was created and distributed entirely by volunteers. According to its first issue, it was "a community publication" and "it was formed in order to encourage a new awareness and involvement among our people." With articles on police brutality, racist government policies, corrupt politicians, health and medicine, and the "P.O.W. Forum"—a series on Black people in prisons—as well as poetry and artwork, Black News worked to fulfill its mission to "agitate, educate, [and] organize." The copies in this collection are facsimiles.
  Please note that some of the article titles in Black News use oppressive language. This language is used in context as verbatim titles from the publication and as such has not been altered in this finding aid.
  - Covers (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Volume 1
    - No. 1, 1969 October (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Contents
      "Black News" of Bedford Stuyvesant
      Explanation Of the So-called Generation Gap
      Radical Approach toward low-income housing
      The Black study circle
      "The Beast" (a poem)
      Make it, Buy it, or Take it
      Black soul plays
      Enemies of the Black community
      The Black Ass Kickin' Brigade
      Forced out of their Home
      "One Bloody Night"
      No School! protest
    - No. 2, 1969 October (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Ocean Hill Brownsville–Revisited-1969-Less Campbell
      Seminar for Black women
      Black people spend $35 billion annually
      Post Revolution thought (a poem)
      Community control of the land
      "I Love America" (a poem)
      Another Black patriot doomed by the pig
      America is so beautiful in the Autumn
      Ho Chi Minh – The man and his plan
    - No. 3, 1969 November (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Why Black solidarity Day?
      Bedford-Stuyvesant Draft Counseling Service
      Seminar for Black women (schedule)
      The realities of New York City politics
      The Healer
      On Black News
      The A.T.A. Evening school of Knowledge
      Black land
      Willie Thompson
      The Uhuru Academy
      Enemies of the Black Communities
    - No. 4, 1969 November 15 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Christmas Nigger
      Harlem's demand for self-determination
      Black Study Circle
      Understanding
      All out race war in U.S. Marines...1970
      Modern Cities and Nigger incompetence
      What's on?
      Bobby Seale
      From Sister to Sister
      Are policemen really pigs or worse?
      Liberty House
      Keep the grapevine buzzin
      Lindsay owes his body and soul
      "The Death Dance" (a poem)
    - No. 5, 1969 December 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Rapping on Racists
      The arrogance of Model Cities
      The soap-opera syndrome
      "The Needle" (a poem)
      His Master's voice
      A Black father's one man crusade against drugs
      A courageous Black woman
      In-built degradation
      Dear Santa: bring me a handkerchief for my head, a banjo for my knee, and some chains for my legs
      Another courageous Black woman
      The 15 demands of the African-American Students Association
      The fat opulent greasy virgin
      The great kindly benevolence of whitey for cats and dogs
      "Man" (a poem)
      Black Presence
      T.W.O.(Third World Cultural Organization)
      White Treachery Vs. the Good negro
      House Niggers
      Announcements
    - No. 6, 1969 December 19 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      The Black Panthers
      "A message to a Black man"(a poem)
      My Sisters, the Black man is the new man of today
      On Auto-suggestion
      The New School
      To the brother in Blue
      The American Tradition of fair Play
      A Poem
      An educational farce
    - No. 7, 1970 January 10 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      So let him die
      Letters to the editor
      To thy own self be true
      When it comes down (a poem)
      Around our way
      The games Black folk play
      On Black nationalism
      The End is the real world
      On watching Niggers stand on a discount liquor store
      The great land grab continues
      In the beginning
      National joint action committee
      The Vision
      You have not (a poem)
      The Trinidad saga boy
    - No. 8, 1970 January 25 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      On correct Black education
      Pig savagery
      The outrageous incompetency of Model
      Cities
      Dig your revolutionary wig
      Gig for white, work for Black
      "Pick up your guns and fight" (a poem)
      Directions 1
      The priceless land value of Bed-Stuy
    - No. 9, 1970 February 15 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Lest Black Youth forget (the American conspiracy to kill Malcolm X)
      Around Our Way
      An oil dream deferred
      More on the C.I.A.
      Onyx Restaurant
      "Blackness" (a poem)
      School decentralization
      "Your own mask" (a poem)
      Black children…the world is yours
      Panther 21
      Where are you going?
      African-American teachers Association
      Recipes for the Black family
      "What America means to me" (a poem)
      Is, or, was there a college for Bedford Stuyvesant?
      Uhuru Sasa School schedule
      Gotta fight for our land (Atlantic Terminal)
      Tribute to EL-Hajj-Malik-El-Shabazz
      Black awareness Day
    - No. 10, 1970 March 7 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      The Daily News Negro reader
      Bread
      Black pride? Some contradictions
      On School Board registration
      End of non-violence
      Letter to the editor
      "Hey Whitey" (a poem)
      Is it racism or is it the truth?
      The Black Truth
      A call to all Black teachers
      Uhuru Sasa speaks
      "I want a white woman"
      "Don't you remember" (a poem)
      The Separatists fantasy
      The East--an Ad
    - No. 11, 1970 March 21 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Message to a dead Black woman
      Guyana as seen by an African-American
      Rap Brown
      Leadership
      A message to parents
      On youngbloods at "Our Lady of Victory"
      "Peace" (a poem)
      Black Power in the Caribbean
      The Lee Berry case
      More lies from the Board of Ed.
      Why Liberals are traitors
      Land and Power
      City services numbers to know
      "Freedom" (a poem)
      "The time has come" (A poem)
      "Souls, Hipness of Blackness (a poem)
      The glories of separation
      Peoples Y
      Make Black Count
      Bushwick's Lance
      "Precedence" (a poem)
      Subway scenes
      Black Revolutionary religion
      A tremendous success
      "Vive Noir" (a poem)
      Crackers who don't like Honkies
      "Slave auction" (a poem)
    - No. 12, 1970 April 10 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      "The Black Me" (a poem)
      She died in Bellevue waiting 5 Hours
      Why your child gets low grades
      "If we die" (a poem)
      "Note to America" H. Rap Brown
      Monster Technology U.S.A.
      The Black Power Conference
      A love story
      The Unholy sons of Shylock
      The Origin of Knowledge
      Letters to the Editor
      Register to serve jury duty
      On positive thinking
      Another form of genocide
      A letter from Trinidad
      To readers of Black News Re: Our Black politicians
      The last Black Ball
    - No. 13, 1970 April 27 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      The nature of the white pig
      Dear Christ, Please give us some students from Our Lady of Victory
      Whitey rapes again
      Slick Waldaba
      Still more on Atlantic Avenue
      More on Waldaba's bill
      The Brothers and sisters for African unity
      White crime in Ithaca
      Afro-American West Indian unity
      Pan-African solidarity committee
      U.S. Marines ready to vamp on Black Trinidadians
      The liberation of Miss Annie
      The Martin Luther King Jr. film
      Flashes
      Slow death of a Black Child
      "Spirit Unrest" (a poem)
      Swahili
      Religion and the Black revolution
    - No. 14, 1970 May 12 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Statement of the Brooklyn Committee in defense of the Black Panthers
      Black Pride? Some contradictions
      Black manhood
      Third estate (a poem)
      Nigger capitalism
      "Black code of conduct" (a poem)
      Unholy alliance
      On uneducated Negroes
      More letters from Our Lady of Victory
      On screwing around
      More letters from O.L.V.
      Cleveland High is on fire
      Elementary Kiswahili
      Terror on Church Avenue
      The Brothers and Sisters for African unity
      Black power conference
      Amerikkka's savagery
      "Nightmare in the morning" (a poem)
      The East
    - No. 15, 1970 May 28 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Shirley Chisholm
      "Revolution" (a poem)
      Oceanhill Brownsville
      Black struggle in Trinidad
      First Citywide Freedom Dance
      Shame at John Jay
      Political alliances
      The brothers and sisters for African Unity
      Bed-Stuy. Threatened
      Community mandate
      "Last letter to the United States government" (a poem)
      Africana studies and research center - Black studies program Cornell University
      Negroes at Wingate
      "The end, death" (a poem)
    - No. 16, 1970 June 12 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Mysticism in the Black struggle
      Nigger pig and a Black woman
      Nigger political cake-walk
      "I the Black woman" (a poem)
      "The Bar-B-Q" (a poem)
      Political challenge to the waterfront
      Black research center
      White wars in America
      Whole wheat bread
      Black power conference in Bermuda
      "Black and white together" (a poem)
      "We is internationally"(a poem)
      Butterfly McQueen
      "Hey Poem"(a poem)
    - No. 17, 1970 July 6 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Uncle Tom rides again
      Repatriation
      Madison Avenue Negro artists
      Black pride ? some contradictions
      Summer festival
      Negro Individualist
      Black doctor speaks
      Ferguson's appeal denied
      East calendar
      "Recipe for ½ Blackness"( a poem)
      A real Negro
      Racism in East New York
      "Words from Africa" (a poem)
      "Role of the Black woman" (a poem)
    - No. 18, 1970 July 23 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Racism versus class
      Black magicians begin summer theater activities
      The East (ad)
      African civilization
      More strange things on Model Cities
      Oedipus Rex
      Uncle Sam Wright
      An appeal to reason...Negroes who support Israel
      Powerless Black nationalists
      Children's time
      Guyana welcomes African Americans and West Indians
      Dr. Kamuzu Banda of Malawi- the new Tshombe of Africa
      "Domestic 13,171" (a poem)
      The new Lafayette theatre
      Hepatitis in Brownsville
      Struggle in Asbury
    - No. 19, 1970 August 15 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Class versus Racism
      Nguzo Saba
      "Black is " (ad)
      A message to the Lower East Side Nigger hippies
      Black destruction of Black land
      Anatomy of a Hog
      Terror at St. John's University
      "Role of the Black Woman" (a poem)
      Themes on Negro power is Black power
      Black appropriation of Black land
      Transit authority's oppression of Blacks